Charles McLean Andrews Collection Concerning Colonial History
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charles McLean Andrews Collection Concerning Colonial History 1623-1800
MSS75765
Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943
1,200 items 3 containers 1 linear foot
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Historian, educator, and author. Chiefly transcripts of manuscripts in various repositories in England. The material relates to admiralty courts and cases as well as trade and political matters.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943.
Subjects
Admiralty--Great Britain--Colonies.; Admiralty--United States.; Commercial law--Great Britain--Colonies.; Commercial law--United States.; Courts--Great Britain--Colonies.; Courts--United States.; Maritime law--Great Britain--Colonies.; Maritime law--United States.
Places
Great Britain--Colonies--Administration.; Great Britain--Commerce--United States.; United States--Commerce--Great Britain.; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States--Politics and government--To 1775.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Historians.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The Charles McLean Andrews Collection Concerning Colonial History was given to the Library of Congress by Evangeline Walker Andrews in 1944.
Additional Guides
Card indexes of the Andrews Collection are available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room. Consult the reference staff for additional information.
Related Material
The Andrews Collection complements the Manuscript Division's foreign copying collection of manuscripts and records relating to American history in British archives.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Charles McLean Andrews are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1863, Feb. 23 Born, Wethersfield, Conn.
1884 A.B., Trinity College, Hartfold, Conn.
1889 Ph.D., Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1889-1907 Professor, Bryn Mawr College, Hartford, Conn.
1895 Married Evangeline Holcombe Walker (1869-1962)
1904 Published Colonial Self-Government, 1652-1689. New York, London: Harper & Brothers
1907-1910 Professor, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1908 Published Guide to the Manuscript Materials for the History of the United States to 1783 in the British Museum and Other Depositories. Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution of Washington
1910-1931 Professor, American History, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1924 Published The Colonial Background of the American Revolution. Haven: Yale University Press
1925 President, American Historical Association, Washington, D.C.
1935 Pulitzer Prize in history, The Colonial Period of American History. New Haven: Yale University Press; London: Oxford University Press
1937 Awarded gold medal for history and biography, National Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y.
1943, Sept. 9 Died, New Haven, Conn.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles McLean Andrews Collection Concerning Colonial History consists of transcripts of manuscripts in various repositories in England and spans the years 1623-1800. The materials were accumulated by Andrews for use in his writings on American colonial history and cover admiralty courts and cases, trade, and political matters. Andrews authored Lists of Transcript from the British Museum and the Bodleian Library... (Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1908) that lists the transcripts acquired by the Library of Congress.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by source of material.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm80075765
Container List
- British Museum (Box 1)
  - Egerton manuscripts 2395, 2543, and 2670, selected folios, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lansdowne manuscripts 1032, folio 128 (Box 1)
- Additional manuscripts 11411, 32695, and 3288, and selected folios and pages, (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Oxford University All Souls College Library, Oxford, England (Box 1)
  - Information on Captain Henry Wilkinson (Box 1)
- Public Record Office (Box 1)
  - Admiralty 1, 2, and 7, selections from various volumes, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Admiralty High Court libel files, 136, no. 210 (Box 1)
  - Admiralty Courts jurisdiction, cases, related matter, and memoranda and extracts from various volumes (Box 1)
  - Admiralty jurisdiction in the colonies, selections from various volumes (Box 1)
  - Admiralty Office, Library manuscript 30 (Box 1)
  - Chancery 54, selections (Box 1)
- Colonial Office 1 and 5, selections from various volumes, (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Colonial Office, selections from various colonial offices and volumes, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Foreign Office, miscellaneous 2 (Box 2)
  - Gifts and deposits 8, vol. 95, Chatham manuscripts 95 (Box 2)
  - Gifts and deposits 24, Shaftesbury papers (Box 2)
  - State papers, vols. 29 and 330, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Treasury, selections from various treasury volumes (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Altham, Emanuel, and John Bridge, letters, 1623-1624 (Box 3)
  - Banister, John v. Brown, John, 1743 (Box 3)
  - Boston News-Letter, May-Aug., 1721, extracts (Box 3)
  - Commissioners for Trade and Plantations, 1735 (Box 3)
  - "Connecticut," Mr. Dudley's papers on the governments of New England and New York, [1693] (Box 3)
  - Correspondence regarding laws of Connecticut, 1728-1733, 1740, 1752 (Box 3)
  - Dartmouth, Lord manuscripts, 1778-1783 (Box 3)
  - Diary of journey from Wilmington, Del., to New York and New England, June-Nov. 1800 (Box 3)
  - Halton, Robert, will and administrative bond, 1748-1749 (Box 3)
  - Headings of book showing the general customs establishment in America prior to 1767, Sept. (Box 3)
  - Laurens, Henry, letterbook, 1767-1771 selections (Box 3)
  - London Chronicle, vol. 26, no. 2031, extracts, 1769 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous trade statistics, vol. 7 (Box 3)
  - North, Lord, establishment of a plantation office, [1734] (Box 3)
  - Reference to the fees in prize cases (Box 3)
  - Robinson, Thomas, complaint to General Court, 1681 or 1682 (Box 3)
  - Russell, Judge Chambers, letter, 1743 (?) (Box 3)
  - A short view of the smuggling trade... and Representation of the Board of Trade... 1733-1734 (Box 3)
  - Sylvester, Joshua, Tobacco..., a poem, 1672 (Box 3)
  - Warren, Joseph, letter, 1775, Apr. (Box 3)